<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The magistrat's dignity, duty, &amp; danger set forth in a sermon preached in the High Church of Edinbvrgh, on the anniversary day of the election of the magistrats.</title>
            <author>Mackqueen, John, d. 1734.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22255</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12741390</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12741390</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51032)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 696:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The magistrat's dignity, duty, &amp; danger set forth in a sermon preached in the High Church of Edinbvrgh, on the anniversary day of the election of the magistrats.</title>
                  <author>Mackqueen, John, d. 1734.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D., and are to be sold by John Vallange ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedicatory signed: John Mackqueen.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, Scottish --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93143:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93143:1"/>
            <p>THE MAGISTRAT'S Dignity, Duty, &amp; Danger, Set forth in a SERMON Preached in the High Church OF <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> On the Anniverſary Day of the Election of the MAGISTRATS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Nehemiah 5.19.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Think upon me, my God, for good, <hi>according</hi> to all that I have done for this people.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Claudianus de 4.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <lg>
                  <l>Conſultatu Honorii.</l>
                  <l>Tu Civem pat remque geras, tu Conſule canctis,</l>
                  <l>Nec tibi, nec tua te moveant, ſed publica vota.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lucanus Lib. 2. de Laud. Catonis</hi> —</bibl>
               <lg>
                  <l>— Patriaeque impendere vitam.</l>
                  <l>Nec ſibi ſed toti genitum ſe credere mundo.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>—</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Commune bonus: nulloſque Catonis in actus</l>
                  <l>ſubrepſit, partemque tulit ſibi nata voluptas.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>John Vallange</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:93143:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93143:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. JOHN HALL of <hi>Dunglaſs,</hi> Lord Provoſt. And to the much Honoured
<list>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Baillies.</head>
                        <item>ARCHIBALD MUIR of <hi>Thorntoun</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>GEORGE CLARK</item>
                        <item>GEORGE HUME</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>JAMES MACLURG Dean of Gild.</item>
                  <item>WILLIAM MEINZIES Theaſaurer.</item>
                  <item>Mr. HENRY FERGUSSON Colledge-Theaſaurer.</item>
                  <item>GEORGE STIRLING Deacon-Conveener.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">And to the reſt of the Honourable Council of the City of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Integrity with which you manage the publick Concerns of the <hi>good Town,</hi> has juſtly raiſed your Reputation a fair and laſting Memorial in the Hearts of the Neighbourhood of the City: the calmneſs of your Tempers, the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of your Proceedings, the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of your joynt Conſultations for their common Welfare, the ſober and
<pb facs="tcp:93143:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>prudent Methods by which you tender the quiet and peace of the Inhabitants, in this difficult Juncture, ſpeak loudly your Care and Diligence is more le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd at their Eaſe and Advantage, than proſtituted to gratify Humor or privat Intereſt:
<note place="margin">Privati pertinacia in publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note> 
               <hi>The great Bane of all Communities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the happineſs of the City, that as the Candor and Juſtice you practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in your private Capacity,
<note place="margin">Tacius <hi>peſſimum veri affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus &amp; judicii veninum ſuaquique utilitas:</hi> idem:</note> in the Purſuit and Conduct of your particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Affairs, pathed the Way to your Riſing to the Dignity you are in ſo you have Carried and do Retain the ſame, in the Eminent Station you now move in, only you have a more Splendid <hi>Theatre,</hi> a more Ample <hi>Sphere,</hi> to Diſplay and Exerce theſe and the other Vertues, you are ſo happily Endowed with; and as theſe Secure you in
<pb facs="tcp:93143:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Minds of the Citizens, from all Suſpition of Diſhoneſty in your Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik Truſt, ſo the Opulency of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, with which God has Bleſſed and Crowned your Induſtry, Elevats you above all Sordid Temptations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, to which the Straitned Condition of others makes them Obnoxious, all which makes Un-prejudiced Men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually Eſteem &amp; Love you, &amp; promiſe much Honour &amp; Felicity to the Place, from your Auſpicious Government.
<note place="margin">Seneca. <hi>Omnium enim ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos illius vigilantia defendit, omnium ovium il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius labor, omnium delicias illius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſtria, omnium vacatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem illius occupatio, ut remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando animam habebat nunquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>I may ſafely Transfer and Apply to you what the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Moraliſts</hi> wrot of <hi>Polybins,</hi> your VValking makes the Indwellers Sleep ſound, you Toil for their Eaſe, you are Bufied that they may more freely follow their Paſtime, you are conſtantly Imployed that they may have releaſe from Trouble; ſo that though you may enjoy ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion, yet no immunity from
<pb facs="tcp:93143:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Care. The fate of all in ſuch conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous places of Authority, if they act conform to the ends of their great Truſt, and their comfort in the day of their ſolemn Account, that they have bent their ſtudy and endeavour this way, more to ſerve the Publick than their own Avarice or Ambition, which many under that Pretence too frequently advance.</p>
            <p>How little you are influenced by Humour or Partiality, I my ſelf am a ſignal Inſtance, that being outed from my Miniſtry for not complying with the preſent Scene of Affairs, yet you have not meaſured your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by the difference of your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, but have kindly remembred my Twenty years Service in the work of the Goſpel among you, by a <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native</hi> with ſuch frankneſs and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, as diſcover the benignity of
<pb facs="tcp:93143:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>your Natures, the impartiality of your Actings, and how far you are above the narrow diviſive Practice of ſome, who confine all their Offices of Charity, Humanity and Juſtice, to thoſe of their own Opinion, and make that the Standard of their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and privat Benefits or Deeds, yea and the <hi>Caracteriſtick</hi> or Mark,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> not only of their own, but of God's Party too.</p>
            <p>Having ſome Inclinations to retire from this publick Place, ſince I can be no more Serviceable in the Station I was once in, I thought it my Duty from the juſt Senſe of your VVorth, and the grateful Reſentment I retain of your Favour, to ſay all this, and in Teſtimony of my Sincerity in Avouching it, to Dedicat this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to your <hi>Honourable Board,</hi> where, that God's Spirit may Preſide,
<pb facs="tcp:93143:5"/>and Direct you in your publick Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, and Proſper your honeſt particular Imploys, is the hearty VViſh and conſtant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble, moſt Faithful, and moſt Obliged Servant, <hi>JOHN MACKQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93143:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>WHen I removed from <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> with Reſolution to take that innocent ſatisfaction in the Society of my Relations, their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from this place, and my conſtant fixedneſs to my Charge in the City depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me of, for ſo conſiderable a time; I left this Diſcourſe, as you now have it, to the care of a particular Friend, in order to be Printed, but my Books being ſeiſed upon by Command of ſome in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, my Papers were ſo ſcattered, that theſe few Sheets came not into the hands they were appointed for, ſo that upon my coming to this place, I was ſurprized to find them here, not expecting but they had been publiſhed at the time I intended, however now you have the Sermon as it was then deſigned.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93143:6"/>
            <p>It was preached in a time, when the City was divided, if not crumbled into Factions, and I never was, nor will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in the ſidings of Popular Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, I delivered theſe plain Truths without any concernedneſs for one Party or other, as by peruſal it may appear to any, and it is well known, that at the time it was delivered, it reliſhed ill with ſome who thought more <hi>Elogies</hi> than are here beſtowed were due to them upon account of their Dignity, whether they deſerved them or no: And a ſlaviſh Custom had ſo far tirannized over ſome in their publick Appearances, meanly through their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Commendations to foſter this Humor in the Magiſtrats, by foiſting into their Diſcourſes ſome <hi>Claw-back</hi> Expreſſions, whereby they were ſoothed in their Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, rather than inſtructed in their Duty.</p>
            <p>Since my entry to the Miniſtrie, I judged it more becoming me, to reprove
<pb facs="tcp:93143:6"/>the Faults of my Hearers, of whatſoever Quality or Degree, than to palliat them, &amp; howſoever this may paſs for Folly in the Opinion of ſome, who make the Favour of theſe <hi>Balaks</hi> on whom they depend, the <hi>Pol-ſtar</hi> of their publick Motions: Yet I had rather with <hi>Micajah,</hi> incur the Diſpleaſure of Men, by telling the Truth, than either offend GOD by lying in his Roome, or through incouraging Men to continue in their ſinful Courſe, flatter them to their Ruine, by hiding their deformities, or repreſenting them to their view, through leſlening perſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cttives.</p>
            <p>I hope a Diſcourſe ſo honestly intended, will leave no bad Impreſſion on theſe who now are, or at any other time may be in truſted with the Government of the <hi>GOOD TOVVN:</hi> It is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of divine Truths, and unbyaſſed Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, they are adjuſted to all times,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> 
               <hi>what
<pb facs="tcp:93143:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>was written before, was written for our Learning.</hi> And this ſmall <hi>Eſſay,</hi> will render no leſs ſeaſonable and uſeful Inſtructions to others in theſe Offices, than it did to them for whom it was firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared: If it conduce to the effectual bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the City, by exciting the Magiſtrats to Zeal and Care for the Publick, by making us all indeavour to be more uſeful to the World, and beneſicial to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Author hath his Wiſh; the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will have the Benefite, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strats will have the Comfort, and GOD will have the Glory.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93143:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Acts <hi>13.36.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>For David after he had ſerved his own Generation, by the will of God, fell on ſleep.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe mind of Man is more eaſily inſtructed, his affections more readily ſwayed by the light and efficacy of an illuſtrious Example, than by a thouſand Precepts or Directions: a ſingle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or precedent of Excellency, ſtrikes more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully on our Fancy, inſinuats it it ſelf more dextrouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into our Memory, is more convincing of our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, more attractive of our Love and influential on our Practice, to beget in us a generous Emulation, than all the Embelliſhments of Rhetorick, or florid Elogies, wherewith ſtudious ſpeculative Men ſeek to adorn or recommend it: Hence it comes, that the Method of writing particular Men's Lives, has been of old in great eſteem, and is now by ſome ingenious men preferred to Annals or Hiſtory, for as the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams contracted in a Burning-glaſs to a point, has greater force, ſo Vertue darts more beautiful Rayes, more irreſiſtable Charms operats with ſtronger Energy when expoſed to our Conſideration in a well-drawn Picture or eminent Pattern.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Miſconceits of Difficulty or Impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wherewith we palliat our Sloth or Negligence are confuted, theſe Chains by which we are fettered from Induſtry and Action, are filed off by the Copy theſe have left us, who with Honour and Succeſs have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed their Duty and Task: We ſee in brave and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Examples, Vertue clothed as it were with Fleſh and Blood, that which in the Writings of it's greateſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93143:8"/>Admirers, is but a dead Letter, in the Harrang's of the moſt eloquent and paſſionate Orators but an ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ſound, is now drawn to the life, made viſible in its beſt features and full Proportion for our incitment and incouragment: For you muſt know the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of excellent Men we read in the Scriptures, are not to be treat by us as Pictures in great men's Galleries, are gazed on by Bours and Idiots, which ſerve for Ornament to the Room, or Divertiſement to the more intelligent, but they are Looking-glaſſes to us, Directories for our life, Patterns for our imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Copys for our tranſcribing; for which end I come now to offer your Religious Attention, that of our Text, <hi>David after he had ſerved his own generation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What ſome have obſerved of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> that his Rule is wrapt up in the example or inſtance he brings, is the Method of the Holy Ghoſt, when <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>I wil walk within my houſe with a perfect heart,</hi> he gives the Character of a Magiſtrat's domeſtick Behaviour,
<note place="margin">pſal. 101.2.</note> what he ſhould be at home as well as abroad: When <hi>Job</hi> ſays, <hi>I put on righteouſneſs, and it clothed me:</hi> he fits a Robe for every good Magiſtrat,
<note place="margin">Job. 29.14.</note> preferable to your preſent diſtinguiſhing ſplendid Attire: When <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſays, <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord,</hi> he draws the Picture of every good Maſter of a Family,
<note place="margin">Joſh. 24.15.</note> who in the defection of others, ſhould make his own Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Chappel for God's Worſhip. When holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">pſal. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>I water my coutch with my tears,</hi> he has ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us a more lively (though not ſo oſtentive) Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracture of a penitent than St. <hi>Francis</hi> with his coule Sandal, Hair-ſhirt, and the other external Trumperie of Mortification, his order can preſent us, ſo here <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid after he had ſerved his own generation,</hi> carries in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a commanding Precedent for us to ſerve ours.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93143:8"/>
            <p>In the Words, we have <hi>David</hi>'s Character and his end, or his Imployment and Liberation there-from, <hi>he ſerved his generation,</hi> that was his Character and Work, <hi>and then fell a ſleep,</hi> he was exoner'd of his Burden: or you may call it his Charge and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, his Toyl and his Reſt: <hi>he ſerved his generation.</hi> This was his Charge and Toyl, <hi>he fell on ſleep,</hi> here his Exemption, Eaſe and Freedome from his Work and Labour. By <hi>Generation,</hi> we are to underſtand men of the Age in which he lived, theſe who were co-temporary with him, whom <hi>David</hi> in his publick capacity did ſet himſelf to Benefite and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, <hi>to ſerve,</hi> theſe was certainly a matter of Toile, Labour and Difficulty, as the word <hi>ſerve</hi> in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal imports, which ſignifies to pull and ſtretch our ſelves as Rowers at the Oar, a violent painful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe; by his <hi>falling a ſleep,</hi> the following words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain this to be, he Dyed, <hi>and was laid into his Fathers, and ſaw Cirruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is uſual in Scripture, to ſet forth Death under the Metaphor of <hi>Sleep,</hi> and all I'l ſay of it, is, it were well we made Sleep a Memorial of it, and that our Bed did put us in mind of our Coffin, Men would not go to their reſt, with Brains ſo diſcompoſed with Exceſs, or hearts impregnated with Malice, as often falls out: This repreſentation of Death, under the term of Sleep, may pare off much of it's frightfulneſs abate much of it's Terrour, it is but a long Sleep, as Sleep is but a ſhort Death.</p>
            <p>We contribute extreamly to our own Diſquiet, we are too ingenious to our own Diſadvantage, by the horrid Schems and terrible Dreſs our imagination pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents Death to us in, while if we ponder right, it is not the things in themſelves, but the appearances of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93143:9"/>them, the Circumſtances we clothe them in, which frequently beget in us an averſeneſs to them: The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God would have us make our ſelves familiar with Death, by viewing and conſidering it often in theſe little Images of it, obvious to our ſenſes and notice, that we may be leſs terrifyed, when it accoſts us in it's true Shape and natural Viſage.</p>
            <p>David <hi>after he had ſerved his own Generation,</hi> &amp;c. What his Service was, we can beſt gather from the Hiſtory of his Life. However we ſhall conſider him here in his publick capacity, ſo I find the Current of Interpreters, take the words as the Character of an excellent Magiſtrat. <hi>David</hi>'s Service was not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted within the narrow Sphere of Self, it was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined within the ſtrait compaſs of his own privat Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, it was not levell'd at his Emolument or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, his Pains, Care, and Trouble, had a larger Circumference, and another Center, even the Men of the Age he lived in, and with, teaching us all to lay out our ſelves, but more particularly theſe in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Stations, for the Advantage and Benefit of theſe we live among; this is truly and properly to ſerve our Generation. But before I proſecute this more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let me hint a little at ſomething implyed in the word <hi>Serve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> being transferred from the hard and laborious Exerciſe of Mariners tugging at the Oar, to repteſent the Magiſtrats Duty and Care.</p>
            <p>Theſe places of Truſt in which Magiſtrats move, for the good and intereſt of others, are not places of eaſe to indulge our lazineſs, or gratify our idleneſs. Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures and Dignities are not the Region of Tranquillity, for all the glitter they make,
<note place="margin">Job 14.1.</note> what <hi>Job</hi> ſays, that <hi>man born of a Woman is of few days and full of trouble,</hi> ſeems to be more peculiarly calculated for publick
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93143:9"/>perſons; the greateſt Laboureres are not thoſe who dig in Mines, or pull in Galleys, no, no, they are clothed in Purple, and carried in Pomp, who ſweat for our reſt, and endure a hundred Tortures for our quiet. The Palace is often but a ſtately Priſon, or a gilded Cage, they Sleep more ſoundly, Feed more cheerfully, and which is far better, they Pray more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently, Faſt more frequently, Chant the Praiſes of the Almighty more melodiouſly, who dwell in Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, ſtretch themſelves on a Couch of Bull-ruſhes, than theſe who ſit under a Canopy of State, and ly upon Beds of Ivory: Wealth is a glittering Burthen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Specioſa ſupplicia</hi> Cypria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> attended with vexing Cares; Honour is a ſplendid Servitude, carrying Torments and Puniſhments under Masks and Diſguiſe; they who have ſhared moſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally of both theſe, have been more happy, &amp; at more eaſe in other Mens opinion, than they were either in reality or in their own apprehenſion: Roſes are no more environed with Thorns than are Thrones, Crowns are lined with Cares, nor are great Mens Chains the weaker for being more curiouſly linked, nor their Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters leſs ſtrong or heavy for being of Gold and not of Iron: yet were this ſomething, if for all their Weight they were not brittle as Glaſs, or weak as Withes of Straw: for all the Pageantry and Parade, for all the Enſigns of Honour and Ornaments of State, theſe who <hi>ſerve the Publick</hi> vapour with; for all the <hi>Hoſanna's</hi> the fickle Populace (which upon a little Diſguſt, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price, or ſudden turn, they ſoon change into <hi>Crucifig's</hi>) ſound in their Ears, while they paſs through the Croud,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magra fortuna magna ſervitus.</hi> Seneca.</note> or enter their ſolemn Aſſemblies, they but for the moſt part, carry a diſcontented Mind under a ſmiling Countenance, a real Slavery under a painted Liberty, a troubleſome Bondage under an appearing Greatneſs.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93143:10"/>
            <p>We may be ſure if this were well weighed and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, there would not be ſuch juſtling for Places, ſuch bandying of Factions, and ſordid Methods for obtaining Dignities in Church and State, as ſome may juſtly be charged with; but I fear many Eye the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and Honour annexed to theſe Preferments, more than the Burthens and Duties of them, or the Care and Diligence they require: and whatever any of you may think of your Advancement, I'll aſſure you, if you anſwer the Ends of it, your Labour and Toil will be greater, and if you idlely indulge your own Eaſe, and proſtitute any Power or Profite which accreſſes by your Places, to ends of Revenge or Riot, of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or Pride, of Injuſtice or Oppreſſion, your Account will be the heavier, and the Burthen of your Doom will exceed that of your Office, or any Temporal Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace or Puniſhment whatſoever.</p>
            <p>I know <hi>ſerving the Publick</hi> is the ordinary Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in the Mouths of thoſe who ſtruggle by Hook and Crook to thruſt themſelves into grand Imployments, but God knows the Avarice and Ambition of ſeverals, advance their Creſt under this Coverture: Many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead <hi>of ſerving the Publick,</hi> ſerve themſelves of it to purpoſe, and Feather their own Neſts out of the Common-Good of theſe Communities they take In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of; I pray God it be not ſo with any that do now, or hereafter may bear Charge in the <hi>Good-Town.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since theſe in eminent Stations are ſingled out for Toil and Trouble, it ſhould make all Governours, and us for them, more inſtant with God, for His Spirit to direct them in the managment of their Truſt, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them under the Burthen and Difficulties they are expoſed to, in the diſcharge of their Offices: <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerves on <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s Prayer for a <hi>double Portion</hi> of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93143:10"/>
               <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Spirit, that it was not ſtrange he ſought a <hi>double Portion,</hi> becauſe he was to live in the Court, in the Sun-ſhine of the Grandeurs and Honours of the World, where the way was more ſlippery, danger more frequent and enticing, while <hi>Elijah</hi> being a man of Afflictions, more retired from the hurry and noiſe of the World, a ſingle Portion was ſufficient for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Comfort; Adverſity not being ſo difficultly born as Proſperity. many, the higher they riſe in the World, loſe ſo much of Goodneſs and Vertue as they acquire of ſecular Grandeur: It is a known Story of <hi>Eulogius,</hi> who from a poor Maſon in <hi>Juſtin</hi>'s time, became great in Wealth and Power, loſt his Integrity and Vertue with the change of his State to the better, and in <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s time, upon his return to his former mean Condition, recovered that Vertue the Opulency of his Fortune,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luxuriant animi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque ſecundis.</hi> Ovid.</note> and the Favour of the Court had drown'd and ſtifl'd. Greatneſs has been Fatal to many, more have been ruin'd by their Dignities than better'd by them, like thoſe Fountains in the <hi>Indies,</hi> which retain their natural freſhneſs &amp; ſweetneſs all the Night over, but are no ſooner ſhined on by the warm Beams of the Sun in the Morning, than they degenerat into ſowrneſs. Have not you known ſome upon their Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, change that Modeſty, Meekneſs, and Humility, which adorned their former Station into Starchtneſs, Inſolency and ſauſie-diſtance-keeping, wherewith they ſought to hide the obſcurity of their Birth, and the meanneſs of their Parts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> All which, wakened others to inquire more narrowly into both, and in end made them fall ſhort of that eſteem they ſo ſiniſtrouſly hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after. Abundance and worldly glory-makes People often forget God, misken themſelves, and neglect their beſt Friends: Proſperity as a heavy Clog makes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93143:11"/>the Soul drive ſlowly in the ways of God, as Bees rol'd in Honey cannot raiſe themſelves; the ſmiling Delights of the World are too great a counterpoiſe to the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Elevations and Mountings of our Spirits; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy Man, who was like to be in danger from them prayes for a <hi>double Portion:</hi> and truly a double Diligence, a double Devotion, a double Watchfulneſs, is little enough for thoſe in ſuch Circumſtances, an ordinary meaſure of Piety, of Care or Circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though it may be proof enough, againnſt any tincture of Vice, wherewith the Temptations of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat condition may aſſault the Soul, yet it may prove too feeble to grapple with the force wherewith Satan ruſhes on, or violently invades thoſe of a higher Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Yet would not <hi>I</hi> by this fright men of Parts and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, of Honeſty &amp; Integrity from thoſe honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Imployes, becauſe of the Burden, Toyl and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger annexed to them, he that fears each danger, ſtartles at every Difficulty, will never interpriſe any Action of Honour or Glory: but as all Merchants muſt not loiter in the Harbour, becauſe others are loſt in the Voyage, nor all Soldiers wallow in their Tents, be-becauſe others walter in their Blood in the Field: if ſome have miſcarried, others have returned with rich Cargoes and Lawrels from their Adventures, no more muſt you decline theſe publick places, although others have ſplited thereupon, ſince in all Ages ſome have been worſe, ſome have been better for their preferments: if we foregoe every thing attended with Hazard, ſtoop to every Oppoſition, ſhrink at every appearing Cloud, or approaching Tempeſt, we will never attempt any thing generous or grand for our ſelves or others: Danger is the very Element of vertue, and Theatre of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93143:11"/>Glory,
<note place="margin">le ventlae tempeſte l'orage monſtrem du la cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</note> nor ſhould we conſider how invidious or peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous the matter is, but how noble and uſeful: Let none of you then, whom providence in a regular way ſhall call to theſe higher Seats, avoid them upon ſcore of trouble or danger, you may by the exerciſe of theſe Gifts which were eclipſed in your Privacy, convert that into matter of Renown, which has had ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant influence upon weaker Conſtitutions, and you may raiſe Trophies for your Honour, from what has been to others precipes of Ruine and Diſgrace.</p>
            <p>It argues Diſpondency of the divine Aſſiſtance, as well as Baſtardlineſs of Spirit, to decline theſe Honours a favourable providence caſts in our way, and a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py concurrance of Circumſtances, through God's bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing may, make us to improve to Gods glory, our Countrey's good, our own and others common Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: It is only the ſneaking ſiniſtrous Methods by which ſome ſcrew themſelves into Places, for which God never fitted them, Nature never qualifyed them, their Breeding neverpoliſhed them, nor were they by Cultivation of parts capacitated for them, that is to be juſtly taxed: but for men of large Souls and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Eſtates, diſpoſed to Acts of bounty and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, regularly to aſcend to theſe publick Stations, where they are ſeconded with Power and Ability, with an ample Theatre for their Magnificence and Bounty: Such men's Advancement is like the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of theſe auſpicious Planets, which purifyes the Air, tempers the Seaſons, fertilizes the Earth, and benefits the world with their Influences. But I believe I need not ſpend time in reconciling men's Affections to publick Imployes, in an Age and Place, where I know there are more Competitors and Candidats for preferment, than there are Dignities to part among
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93143:12"/>them; there is as little fear of ſom's abſtractedneſs this way, as of rich beautiful Maids among us turning <hi>Nuns,</hi> or opulent young Heirs becoming blind with Studying, or mad with Learning.</p>
            <p>When we moderat our Deſire of worldly things, and propoſe Noble and Excellent Ends in the fruition of them, when we wiſh them for ends of Neceſſity or Conveniencie, for honeſt and innocent Purpoſes, they become rational: But beſides theſe ends, if we extend our Deſires of them further to ſpiritual Uſes, if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Riches, not only to ſupply our Wants, but to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe our Charity, if we covet Power to curb the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency of the Injurious, and help the Oppreſſed, if we ſeek Honour not only to ward-off Contempt, but to make our Vertue more Illuſtrious and Influential on others, to have a ſplendid Sphere for diſplaying it's Rayes, and alluring others to it's Admiration and Liking, then our affection to Places of Honour and Truſt, and ſuch ſecular Objects becomes Heavenly, Purifyed and Refined: It commences into the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion, it becomes a ſpiritual Inſtrument, for furtherance of our everlaſting Felicity.</p>
            <p>However the Conſideration of the Toyl and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of thoſe who ſerve the Publick in honourable Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhould check Inferiors envying their Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; every Glance on their Stare, ſhould invite our Prayers in their behalf, rather than their imaginary Splendor provoke our Envy, Care and Trouble we ſee are their Companions of greatneſs, Vanity and Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, are in a more ſpecial manner the Appennags of publick Places, the Curſe thundered out againſt the Earth of <hi>bringing forth Briars and Thorns,</hi> ſeems par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly levll'd at the higher Ground: and to raiſe this a little higher, if Subjects knew the black Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſms
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93143:12"/>of Care, Fear, and inward Diſcontents, which attend the Monarchs of the World, and they drag with them to their Thrones, and from them to their Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets, which make their Meals many a time heartleſs, their Sleeps unequal, their Pillows of Silk and Beds of ſtate uneaſie, their ſumptuous Fare diſguſtfull, they would not ſo much envy their Condition or be diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentented at their own.</p>
            <p>Let us then be taught by this Reflection, Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with our our private State, ſince we are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſecured from many Difficulties and Temptations: It had been good for ſome they had never been ſo great, they had ſleeped longer in a whole Skin, and retained longer a ſound Conſcience, they had had few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Snares, leſs Guilt, and eaſier Cares: they had with ſafety eſcaped theſe Traps, Sins and Inconveniencies, into which Satan's Cunning, mans Mallice, and there our Vanity precipitated them many a time. The Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that has aſſigned us our lot, has meaſured it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for us, than if we were our own Carvers; and I am ſure, if we have leſs Dignity than others, we have leſs account to make hereafter, and leſs danger to ſtrugle with for the preſent: But if it come to our turn to be exalted higher in Honour or Power, if we follow the Precedent ſet before us in our Text in his <hi>publick-ſpiritedneſs,</hi> our honourable Poſt and temporal acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations will give reputation to our parts by making them more conſpicuous, we will have the Comfort, and others the Benefite, that we faithfully and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſerved our generation,</hi> which is <hi>Davids</hi> Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>David after he had ſerved his generation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Text lays before us the Character of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Magiſtrat, for we will conſider <hi>David</hi> here in his publick and politick Capacity, and it affords us this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93143:13"/>Concluſion, that <hi>Magistrats ſhould be men of publick ſpirits,</hi> imploying their Power, Parts and Abilities, for the common Advantage and Intereſt of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple over whom they are ſet: This was the great praiſe of all the <hi>Worthies</hi> advanced into the Government a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People of <hi>Iſrael: Moſes</hi> ſtands in the Gap for them, although they were a ſtif-necked People in reference to God, and very ungrate and ungovern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as to himſelf, yet when God offered to take him off from intreating for them,
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.10.</note> by telling, <hi>I'le make of thee a great Nation, let me alone, that my wrath may wax hot againſt them:</hi> He would not forbear, <hi>Moſes</hi> was of another Spirit than many among us, who care not what come of the Publick, whether it riſe or fall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it thrive or periſh, if they can ſit at a full Table, and ſleep in a ſound Skin: <hi>I'le make of thee a great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> What a Temptation this would have been to thoſe who ſcruple at nothing, leave no Stone un-turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as we ſay) to raiſe their Families, though on the Ruine of their Neighbours, yea, and will not ſtand to tread on the neck of their beſt Friends to ſerve their own ends:
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> preferr'd the proſperity of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to his own Grandeur, he made choice to ſhare <hi>in their Affliction, before the Riches and Honour of Egypt: Yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 32.32.</note> his Zeal for the Publick flew higher, when he was content to forego his Happineſs, that they might not miſs <hi>theirs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sumus magnorum Exemplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores,</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt.</note> Did not the ſame publick Spirit act <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hojedah</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah, Mordecai,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah, Jeremiah</hi> and St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and O! <hi>what punie Followers are we of this cloud of Witneſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To convince you how much you are all concerned to advance and promot the common Advantage of one another, and the <hi>publick well,</hi> view the whole frame of Nature, and you'l ſee there is nothing created for it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93143:13"/>ſelf, but ſo placed by the Divine Providence, that it may contribute to the good of others: all that is moſt excellent in Nature, is moſt communicative and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficent, as if with on conſent they conſpired to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Selfiſhneſs: The great Luminaries of Heaven, the Waters of the Ocean, the Fruits of Trees, the Folw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Meadows; theſe are for the Pleaſure, Uſe and Benefite of others, as well as for the Beauty and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of the Univerſe: The more noble any thing is,
<note place="margin">Cauſſin's <hi>holy Court Diſcourſe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs.</hi>
               </note> it is ſo much the more uſeful, and as an eloquent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has it, <hi>the great things of the World were made to ſerve the leſſer,</hi> 
               <q>God would not that the great things ſhould be great in vain, but that they ſhould pay for their greatneſs, by the favours and care they were to take for the little ones, Kings and Monarchs are for the Peopl's Safety and Preſervation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Royalty is an invention of God, appointed not for the benefite of Kings, but of the Common-wealth, it was not inſtituted for the Vain glory of Men, but for the ſafety of the Univerſe, and Princes are more for the Peopl's ſake, than the People for theirs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It were happy if Rulers of all Degrees did believe this, and act accordingly, then they would not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the lawfulneſs of their Practices, by the length of their Sword, or the ſtrength of their Arm,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ferrique poteſtas confundit jus omne manu</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. lib. 1. <hi>circa fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
               </note> Men were never cloathed with Power to uſe it Arbitrarly, to ſerve their Avarice with the Goods, or their Revenge with the Blood of their People: if theſe whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is abſolute, did ſtretch it no further than they ſhould, did they count nothing Glorious but what is Juſt, nothing Magnifick but what is Vertuous, their Power would prove the Bull-wark of their People, and the Peoples Lives and Fortunes would be the Support of their Grandeur, and the Security of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93143:14"/>ſince then the doing good to others, is the Language of the whole Creation, and the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things are the moſt uſeful, we moſt not think God has given Men Natural Gifts, Temporal Acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations, Spiritual Endowments, for themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: No, no; what is withheld from this Common and Univerſal End, is a piece of Monopoly, Theft, or Sacriledge,
<note place="margin">Brutus <hi>exuit pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum ut conſulem ageret</hi> Valcrius Max. lib. 5. cap. 8.</note> which God will enquire after, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly puniſh.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sages</hi> of <hi>Gentiliſm</hi> without any other Light, than what they received in the <hi>Sinai</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they were born Tributaries to their Countrey, Zeal for the Honour of the State with them, ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up all thoughts for their own Eaſe or Domeſtick Concern:
<note place="margin">Plutarch vit. Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rg. <hi>vircit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dumque immenſa cupido</hi> Virg. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid. lib. 6.</note> this ſo far ſwayed them, it did preponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, that Natural Affection to their Children, Care of their own particular Honour and Reputation, Love of Life, and all things elſe, which have moſt Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent over Men.</p>
            <p>How it ſtiffl'd in them Natural Affection, we have an inſtance in <hi>Brutus,</hi> who with a ſtern Countenance and ſtout, but yet ſerene Heart, ordered from his Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Tribunal, his two Sons to be whipt to Death in his own Preſence, for Conſpyring to ſubvert their Countrey, and proſtitute it to the Tyranny of the <hi>Tarquins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non ego te</hi> Catili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Patriam ſed Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus</hi> Catili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nui</hi> Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius <hi>Max.</hi> lib. 5. cap. 8.</note> from which it was newly liberated. <hi>Fulvius</hi> without pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Youth, or regarding the blooming hopes ſo apparant in his Son, in whom Nature had engraven all the rare Accompliſhments, capable of Politneſs and Improvement by Art, cauſed put him to Death for joining with <hi>Catiline,</hi> telling he begot him, <hi>to ſerve his Countrey againſt</hi> Catiline, <hi>and not to ſerve</hi> Catiline <hi>againſt his Countrey. Pharnaces</hi> King of the <hi>Parthians</hi> when he was dying, bequeath'd the Kingdom to his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93143:14"/>Brother, becauſe better qualified, rather than to any of his own Sons, ſaying, he <hi>held himſelf more tyed to their publick State, than to his Family, and that it was mor incumbent on him to provide for the Kingdom, than for his Poſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But howſoever a high Pitch of Maſculine Spirit in ſome <hi>Heroes,</hi> or a piece of <hi>Roman Gallantry</hi> in others, or ſome will ſay an obdur'd Temper, or ſome Politick Conſideration might choak all Natural Sentiments, in thoſe of a more hardy Conſtitution,
<note place="margin">Plutarch vit. Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgi.</note> yet to ſee the <hi>Spartan Matron</hi> counter-act the Genuine Tenderneſs of her Sex, the Peculiar Weakneſs of old Age, ſo ſubject to repining Grief, the fond Affection of a Mother, to ſee her Generoſity and Magnanimity tranſport her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all Humane Tyes, to rejoice in the Death of her Sons, when it was for the Ranſom of her Countrey, to ſee her Maſter ſo great a Diſaſter, and patiently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the Fruſtration of ſo great Hopes, as ſhe might ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally expect from ſuch promiſing <hi>Sparks,</hi> and all this from a Principle of Zeal for the Honour and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of her Countrey, is ſuch an inſtance as may at once ſtrike us with Wonder and Admiration of her Vertue, and a juſt deteſtation of the Mean-ſpiritedneſs, ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally predominant amongſt us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others to uphold the Reputation and Intereſt of their Countrey, ſacrificed their own Honour, than which nothing is dearer to <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>Spirit,</hi> it was this which put Life and Motion into all their Actions of <hi>Bravery,</hi> yet upon Competition, they did chooſe to Forfeit their own to ſave their Countrey's Credit, ſo <hi>Catulus</hi> when the <hi>Roman</hi> Army fled ſhamefully againſt his will, he ran and marcht on their head,
<note place="margin">Plutarch vit. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii.</note> that they might be concluded not ſo much to have turn'd their backs to their Enemies through Cowardice, as to have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93143:15"/>made an orderly Retreat at the Command of their General, deſirous by this, the Diſgrace ſhould rather fall on himſelf, than his Countrey. This made the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> in Deſpection of his own Parts, rejoice, <hi>there were three hundred found in the City, fitter for the publick Magistracy than himſelf.</hi> This inſpired ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that Nation, when he came on an Embaſly, to treat for ſome honourable Conditions to his Countrey,
<note place="margin">Plut. vit. Lycurgi.</note> he was demanded whether he came of himſelf, or by Authority of the <hi>Ephori,</hi> to make that bold and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Anſwer, <hi>if I ſpeed I came from the Governours of</hi> Sparta, <hi>but if I am repulſed, I came of my own head:</hi> ſo loath was he to expoſe either the Credit or Authority of the <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> to be flouted at by being denyed in any thing, and would rather take with a guilt he was free of, than that that it ſhould be thought the great <hi>Miſtris</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> for Policy, was of ſo little Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, as to have ſent them a <hi>bootleſs Errand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this general Concernedneſs for their Countrey, not only made ſome famous Men counteract Nature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunce their Honour, but lay down their Lives, yea ſeek out and fiſh for Opportunities of Death, to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the flouriſhing of the State, at the expenſe of their Lives,
<note place="margin">Vallerius Paterc. lib. 1. <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca initium</hi>
               </note> in the War betwixt the <hi>Athenians,</hi> and ſome Neighbours, when the <hi>Reſponſe</hi> of the <hi>Oracle</hi> was, that <hi>whoſe King was kill'd, that Kingdom ſhould conquer: Codrus</hi> their <hi>Monarch</hi> laying by all the Marks and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of his Princely Dignity, putting himſelf in a mean contemptible Dreſs, that he might not be known to be their King, thruſt himſelf into the thickeſt of the Enemy, where he was ſure to be over-power'd, and ſo deſignedly preſerved his <hi>Countrey</hi> with his own <hi>Ruine.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dignoſci arduum eſt utrum Romana civitas u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilius ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios <hi>duces an amiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vita corum ne vinceretur obſtitit, mors facit ut vince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</hi> Valerius Max. lib. 5. cap. 6.</note> So did the <hi>Decii</hi> of whom it was ſaid, <hi>it was hard to determine, whether their Lives or their Deaths
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93143:15"/>contributed more to the Glory and Safety of</hi> Rome, <hi>in their Life their Valour made it Victorious, and by their Death it became Triumphant over all it's Enemies,</hi> but if any will ſatisfy his Curioſity with more inſtances of this kind, let him look that Compend of <hi>Heroiſm</hi> by <hi>Valerius Maximus, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Lucan</hi>'s <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Cato, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 380.</p>
            <p>But what need we wade into <hi>Heathen</hi> Authors, for Examples of this Nature, where they are often Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with <hi>Romantick Gloſses,</hi> or at beſt mix'd with much Droſs and Allay, let us raiſe our thoughts and faſten our eyes on thoſe we have named,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ſine Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto omnis virtus in vitio eſt.</hi> Hierom. <hi>in Epist. ad</hi> Gal.</note> preſented to our Conſideration in <hi>Scripture,</hi> theſe will have a leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Impreſſion on us, and excite in us a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as well as a more innocent Emulation, their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are inſpired by a nobler Principle, illuminated by a clearer Light, levell'd at a higher Elevation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>infidelium virtus i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolum eſt, cujus ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda, ſed virtus inanis.</hi> Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note>
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Tincture of vain Glory, which as a <hi>threed</hi> ran through and twined it ſelf with the ſplendid Actions of <hi>Infidels, theſe, theſe</hi> are of a purer Complexion, and ſtronger Efficacy, than thoſe which act by the Spirit of the <hi>World,</hi> or Maxims of <hi>Morality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Material World</hi> in it's Bulk and Parts, if the <hi>Pagan World</hi> in it's eminent <hi>Heroes,</hi> be againſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Drifts to the prejudice of the <hi>Publick,</hi> the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World</hi> is as remote from all narrow Self-aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or private Byaſſes, therefore conſider in the <hi>third place,</hi> if Nature and Humanity would have us Communicative, Grace is not for our being Niggard, of what the Bounty of Heaven has committed to us: it is ſet forth under the Notion of a <hi>Fountain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14.14.</note> or a <hi>Well of Water,</hi> which freely ſprings, conſtantly flows, and largely ſtreams, to water all about it, there is nothing pinches or ſtraitens the Soul like ſin, nor is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93143:16"/>it ever ſo freely inlarged, as when it is impregnated with Grace, when it dilates it ſelf upon the Divinity, and feeds upon Celeſtial Objects, theſe ennoble, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliat, and extend it, the nearer any Beeing comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, who is infinit Fullneſs, the more it reſemble him, and partake of his Nature, it is by ſo much the more Diffuſive and Beneficial: and the further it ſlides from him, it is ſo much the more ſtraitned and confined: nothing enſlaves the Soul like low ſelfiſh ends, nor does it ever act more freely or fully, than when it expatiats it ſelf upon God, for ſo it expands it ſelf in ſome proportion to the divine Nature, to ſet forward the Benefit and Advantage of others. If you would ask a devout Soul, when is it he has moſt inlarged Deſires and Deſigns of Benificence? His anſwer would be, he finds himſelf moſt Un-bounded, when he is under the moſt powerfull Conſtraints of divine Love, and the gracious Influences of infinit Goodneſs. Every thing is ſo much the more noble,
<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>quo longiores habet fines,</hi> as the Sphere of it's Activity and ends are exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, Grace opens the Heart, and ſtretches out the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections towards others,
<note place="margin">Acts 4.34.</note> ſo it did in thoſe new Converts, who before this work of Grace, were both ſtrait hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſtrait-handed: ſin contracts the Affections and manacles the hands from charitable and generous Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but when Grace has made it's Entry and Conqueſt, Mans Soul is more inlarged, the Cirle of his Actings more ample, and he himſelf becomes more bountifull to Mankind, and uſeful to the World.</p>
            <p>And no Wonder, ſince all Chriſtian Societies are as a <hi>Politick Myſtical Body,</hi> in need of one anothors mutual Aſſiſtance, the Variety that is obſervable in the whole frame of Nature, is one of it's greateſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, the Diverſity of Functions in the Natural
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93143:16"/>Body, with the mutual Harmony of it's parts, gives no ſmall Luſtre to it's Beauty, and the difference of Conditions in the <hi>Body Politick,</hi> is at once it's greateſt Decency and Safety, and as the divine Providence has made this agreeable Mixture of High and Low, Rich and Poor, Magiſtrats and Commons, for the Profit as well as Pleaſure of all, the neceſſary Service of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals, as well as for the comely Order of the whole, Charity which is the Cement of Chriſtian Societies, ſhould make our Contentments common, rejoice in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers good fortune, without grudging or interferring with one another, join heart and hand, to encourage and promot one anothers Intereſt, with a Subſerviency to the publick and common Felicity of the Place.</p>
            <p>This the divine Apoſtle ſets forth with equal ſtrength of Reaſon &amp; Eloquence,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.</note> in the friendly Imployes of the parts of the Natural Body, which are ſerviceable to the whole, &amp; to one another, the eye ſees not for it ſelf, but for the Body, the hand works not for it ſelf, but for the Body, ſo that to prefer a private good before the publick is to tranſcribe his folly, who would famiſh his whole Body to fatten a toe, or ſave his finger. We ſee in Nature, the great Fabrick of the World is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Reciprocal Friendſhip and Confederacy of it's Parts, which, ſhould they univerſally fall out, and break the Bond of Unity, that is betwixt them, ſhould they act their <hi>Antipathies</hi> upon each other, yea ſhould they but ceaſe to ſerve one another for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral good, the whole <hi>Machine</hi> of Heaven and Earth would be diſſolved, and all things ſhuffled into Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Ruine. The great <hi>Animal</hi> of a <hi>Republick</hi> has as much conſent of Parts, as much need of one another's friendly ſupply, the Repreſentation of this in that pretty <hi>Apologue</hi> of <hi>Menenius Agrippa</hi> reclaimed the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93143:17"/>Common-people that <hi>beast of many heads,</hi> but <hi>few eyes</hi> and <hi>little brains,</hi> to their Duty after their ſeditious Revolt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He told them,
<note place="margin">Plutarch <hi>vita Cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clani.</hi>
                  </note> there fell a diſcord betwixt the Stomach and the members of the Body, they accuſed it, as devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all, and doing nought, while they toiled and fatigued to ſerve and uphold it, in the mean time ſhe aſſerted, that by her providence, all ſhe received, was expended and communicated, for the uſe and ſustenance of the other parts, without whoſe Cares and Pains, they would have famiſhed and become unfit for Motion or Action: and this was the caſe of the People of</hi> Rome, <hi>and the Senat, which houſbanded whatever it received for their behove, and by it's prudent Managry, reſerved it for their need, upon neceſsitous Emergents, and fit Opportunities diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted the ſame, ſo as it circulated to ſupply, and anſwer the Indigencies of all the Parts, of the vaſt Body of the Common wealth,</hi> by this familiar and witty compariſon, he deſcribed truly the nature of their State, appeaſed the fury of the <hi>Multitude,</hi> and made them cheerfully reſign themſelves to the Conduct of their Governors.</p>
            <p>Now theſe four Reaſons from Nature and Morality, Grace and Policy may convince us, how juſtly this <hi>Publick ſpiritedneſs</hi> may be expected from us all, but more peculiarly from you, <hi>my Honourable Patrons,</hi> whoſe Station, Capacities, and Abilities are more cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated for this end, in a more eminent manner, than the Circumſtances of others can qualify them for, and as I doubt not of your Zeal, to imploy your Truſt for the Honour and Intereſt of the City, ſo that you may do it ſuceſsfully, take theſe following Directions, as ſo many helps to that Purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Piety</hi> qualifies Magiſtrats, to act worthily for the Publick, I may well begin with this, for <hi>it has the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93143:17"/>ſame Preeminence among the Graces,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Philo.</note> which God has among Beeings:</hi> other Vertues requiſite in Rulers will miſcarry, without this lay the Ground-work, they will make a glittering ſhew, without they be enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and enliven'd by this, it is this that ſanctifies their Policies, from this they may expect a happy Event to their Undertakings, things have never ſucceded better under any Mans Conduct, than under theſe, who ſeek the Direction &amp; Aſſiſtance of Heaven, it is no Wonder, theſe who have ſuch Power and Favour with God, by the pious and welcom Violence of their Prayers, the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduity of their Devotion, ſhould have an auſpicious influence on the happy ordering publick Affairs to their deſigned end: <hi>the Religion of Rulers is the beſt Angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guardian of the City, and Superintendent of it's common Concerns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> concluded,
<note place="margin">Plutarch vit. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celli.</note> the flouriſhing &amp; Proſperity of the Common-wealth, depended more on the Senats zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Care of the matters of Religion at Home, than on the Power &amp; Policy of their Armies abroad, &amp; therefore they imputed the bad Succeſs of their Affairs, to ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect or defect in their Religious Services: your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Chriſtian regular walk in your own Families, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be not obvious to others, yet is not leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, leſs Comfortable to you, or leſs influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to proſper your publick Proceedings: the Prayers of the Cloſet although leſs conſpicuous, yet is not leſs vigorous to bring the Benedictions of Heaven on your Actings, at the Council Table, were we all more exact and more conſcientious in our private Houſes, Selfiſhneſs, and Partiality, Revenge, and Pride, would not mingle ſo much with our Adminiſtrations,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.2.</note> to the prejudice of the Publick. <hi>David</hi>'s care to <hi>walk in his own houſe with a perfect heart,</hi> fitted him the better to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93143:18"/>ſway the Sceptre of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> there are ſome Magiſtrats who compoſe themſelves to a decent Carriage, a grave Deportment, a modeſt Behaviour, while they walk the Sreets, ſit at the Council-board, frequent ſolemn Aſſemblies, or meet on publick buſineſs, they are then hemm'd in by the multitude of Witneſſes, over-awed by the Ceremonies of their place, but trace them home, you'll find them little better, than incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Devils there, you'll ſee them domineering Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, unnatural Parents, and imperious Maſters: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have been admired abroad, in whom neither the the Wife or Servant, could behold any thing Praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy at home, theſe Magiſtrats run the fate of ſuch <hi>Prophets,
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.57.</note> who are not honoured in their own Countrey:</hi> Reſpect is certainly, the very ſoul of Government, the great Charm to tye humane minds; to a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjection to their Superiors, and where this is wanting, no Power or Policy of Rulers, can make the obedience of Inferiors cordial or laſting. Piety infuſes Awfulneſs into their Countenances, and Authority in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Commands, people will never readily or from the heart obey theſe, who maintain not the Honour of their Character by Religion and Vertue.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Piety</hi> will introduce <hi>Self-denyal</hi> into the Soul, than which I know no better diſpoſition towards Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats,
<note place="margin">☞</note> acting zealouſly for the publick, <hi>Publick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with private Aimes, are the ruine of Church and State, of City and Countrey, while private Perſons with publick ſpirits are the ſupporters thereof: Selfe-love</hi> is the Original of all the diſorders in the univerſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>faevior eſt tanto quanto eſt occultior hoſtis.</hi> Claudian</note> a Perſon can neither be a good Chriſtian, or a good Magiſtrat, ſo long as he is byaſſed thereby, the City had as good guard againſt a ſelfiſh Magiſtrat, as a Common Foe; for of the two he is the moſt dangerous Enemy, has
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93143:18"/>greater Advantages, and fairer Opportunities to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure it: It is large Souls more than large Eſtates which capacitats Men for great undertakings, theſe who are content to be poor in a rich City, rather than Rich in a poor Community, are certainly more likely to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age it's Concerns for the publick Well-fare of the Place, ſuch will never make the Common-good a Stale to the intereſt of a factious Party, or enrich themſelves at it's coſt. Search the Scriptures or Humane Stories, you'll hardly find any Commended for their care of the Publick, without this ſelf-denyal: Carnal ends, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Affections, domeſtick Intereſts, uſually obſtruct noble Enterpriſes, men ſubject to Impreſſions from theſe, in time of any Storm or Difficulty go foreward or backward for the ſervice of the Publick, as they ſee it conſiſtent with their own temporal Safety, or perſonal Security.</p>
            <p>Pray you abandon your private Aimes, and ſelfiſh narrow Deſigns, look not a-ſquint to your own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, when the Publick is in Danger, call to mind the ſolemn Proteſtations you have reiterated, the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made againſt ſome of your Prediceſſors, how juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or unjuſtly my Buſineſs is not in this place, or at this time to inquire into, conſider the Expectation people have conceived of you, upon your getting the Reins of the Government into your hands, if you embazle the common Stock to increaſe your own, if you raiſe your Fortuns on the Ruine of the Towns Treaſure, or imploy it to ends of Luxury or Riot, you falſifie your Oaths, you'll get a Sting in your Souls, a Blot in your Names, which will out-live your Authority, and daſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>your Memories with Infamy and Reproach.</p>
            <p>But if in ſtead of this narrow Self-confinement, we transfer our <hi>Love</hi> to the Publick, and ſuffer it to dilate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93143:19"/>it ſelf in proportion to the large extent of it's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, this widening and amplifying it's Object, is ſo far from weakning it's force, that it fortifies and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhes our Souls with ſtrong Inclinations and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Reſolutions to advance it's Intereſt, to withſtand whatever is level'd directly againſt it, or may have a Tendency to it's detriment: This will make Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats indefatigable in their pains for the publick, and inflexible to all the Temptations wherewith others ſeek to corrupt their Integrity: We ſee what Miracles this paſſion is able to produce, when it terminats on ſome ſorry Objects, it is not frighted with Dangers, nor chock'd with Difficulty, it is not ſtiffl'd with Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or diverted with Diſcouragments, it looks on all theſe as Tryals of its ſtrenght, and occaſions of it's Triumph, and truly it has afforded the World no leſs matter of wonder in theſe many <hi>Hero's</hi> upon record, who were inflam'd thereby to welcome Death with all the Harbingers of Terrour, Circumſtances of Horrour, and dreadful Conſequences, wherewith the ingenious Cruelty of ſome inhumane Monſters preſented it to them, rather than ſurvive their Countrey's Liberty and Glory. St. <hi>Paul</hi> confounds all the <hi>Graces</hi> with <hi>Charity,</hi> as if they were not ſo different in Nature as in Name from it; No winder it is the Soul that quickens and acts them all, and as the paſſions are nothing but the Lackeys of Love, ſo we may ſay all the Vertues requiſite in a Magiſtrate, are the Miniſters of <hi>Charity,</hi> this will ſet his prudence on work to diſcern the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of acting, as well as the nature of theſe things which conduce to the Hurt or Well of the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: This will make him juſt, though to his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, for the benefite of the Society, it will make him with ſuch <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> hold the Reins
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93143:19"/>ſo evenly, that the City ſuffer not by fooliſh Pity or cruel Severity: and it will inſpire him with <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> and <hi>Fortitude,</hi> than which I know no Vertue more neceſſary to men in publick Stations, to carry them through in acting for the common Advantage.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore in a particular manner recommend <hi>it</hi> to you, as that which will make you invincible to the aſſaults of the Great, Immoveable with the Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Envyous, and victorious over the Clamors of the Rabble. Indeed Love to the publick in the Civil, is like the <hi>Sun</hi> in the Natural World, the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter and Cheriſher of all that conduce to it's Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Preſervation; yet as the <hi>Sun</hi> in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has it's different Manſion houſes, in which his influences are various, in ſome more, in ſome leſs Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigne and Forcible, ſo this <hi>Love</hi> to the Publick exerc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es it's Efforts, with more or leſs Vigour, as it is in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with thoſe divine <hi>Habits,</hi> but with none is it more Triumphant than with this <hi>Chriſtian Fortitude,</hi> here he darts his moſt refulgent Beams, here he makes his moſt vigorous Sallies, here he makes his braveſt Conqueſts, here he makes his ſtouteſt Reſiſtance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all violent Invaſions, here he practiſes the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Warchfulneſs againſt the cunning Incroachments on the Goods and Properties of theſe he has charge of,</p>
            <p>If this <hi>Fortitude</hi> had not animated the firſt Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Empires, the <hi>State</hi> had periſhed in it's <hi>Swadling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,</hi> had not this born them up in the purſuit of their great projects, they had fainted in the Way, and did it not accompliſh their Exploits, their former Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances had been repell'd with diſgrace, they loſe the Reward of all their Labour, and their Names dyed without Elogies or Applauſe: This has made famous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93143:20"/>Men chooſe Death with all it's frightful Appearances, rather than a Life of pleaſure and eaſe, while their Nation loſt it's Honour: they coveted not to retain ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life or Liberty longer than thereby they could ſerve and ſave their Countrey, and when they expir'd in it's quarrel, were cruſh'd with it's Ruine, they raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed laſting <hi>Arches</hi> for their glory.</p>
            <p>We need not ſearch the Rolls of <hi>Greece,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Region of Romances for inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Heroick Courage,</hi> or this <hi>publick Gallantrie</hi> of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, not only the Chriſtian World, but our own <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> afford Examples of undaunted Bravery, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick-ſpiritedneſs: Many who loved not their Lives to the Death, but were hailed to Priſons, martyr'd on Scaffolds, fell Victimes to the Fury of a popular Rabble, preferring an honourable Death to an infamous Life, which they counted ſuch if they ſurvived, though with all affluence of Wealth, pleaſure and honour their Countreys glory</p>
            <p>It is this <hi>Fortitude</hi> which makes men in power and place, contemn great Dangers, conceive great things, combat great Hardſhips for the Publick, it is not want of Power but want of Courage in Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats, that the Weak become a prey to the Strong, and innocency is born down by Injuſtice and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: This will ingadge them to eſpouſe ſtoutly the cauſe of afflicted <hi>Widows</hi> and diſtreſſ'd <hi>Orphants,</hi> againſt thoſe mighty <hi>Nimrods,</hi> or ſtrong Oppreſſors, who ſeek to maintain their Vanity, Luxury, and Pride, and ſupport the declining Grandeur of their Families, with their Portion and Patrimony: There are ſome Relicts and Off-ſpring of honeſt Merchants and Labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tradſ men in the <hi>GOOD TOWN,</hi> which need your aſſiſtance upon this Account, nor is there great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93143:20"/>Oppreſſion or Injuſtice in any obſcure diſtant Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Kingdom, than what is committed through Force and Fraud on ſome of the Inhabitants of this City, the publick Seat of Juſtice, in which to my cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge, many who to keep up their former Reputation, ſeek under a baſhful Modeſty to conceal their Straits, hide their hard Condition under a fair Countenance, viſit their Neighbours Houſes with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Stomachs, where they ſit picking their clean Teeth after many a ſorry Meal, rather than diſcover their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities to the World, while others vapour it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſly, feed highly, fair ſumptuouſly, and are gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly apperrell'd with their Suſtenance, the parings of whoſe Exceſs, or the Tenths of what they juſtly owe them, might afford them tollerable, if not comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Relief.</p>
            <p>It is this wich makes a Magiſtrat equally unſhaken with the Threats of the Mighty,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>juſtum &amp; tenacem propoſiti virum non civium ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>mente quatit ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lida.</hi> Horat. Lib. 3. Carm. Od. 3. ☜</note> or the Menaces of the <hi>Mob,</hi> this makes him alike untouch'd with the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Frowns, or pleaſing Flatteries of all that accoſt him, his Love to the publick makes him bold in it's Defence, while a Coward will betray it through Fear, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert it through Folly and Falſhood, <hi>a timorous perſon can never be honeſt to God or Man,</hi> but he that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with Fortitude, <hi>to ſerve his generation,</hi> is trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant over Fears and Favours, over Honour and Diſgrace, over the Affronts and Court-ſhip of all above about, or beneath him, and deſerves the Venetian Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>Nec fluctu nec flatu movetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Magiſtrat that is acted by theſe Principles, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned with theſe Qualities I have laid before you, need not rgard much the Jealouſies of ſecret, or the Oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies of more avowed invidious Enemies, the honeſty of men in publick Places, may ſecure them from Guilt,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93143:21"/>even upon all Turns and Revolutions, but neither their Prudence or Innocency, can ward off the Envy of ambitious men, or the quarrellous Clamors of the Populary.</p>
            <p>You that ſerve in theſe <hi>Creditable Offices,</hi> may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, ſo long as there is any Competition among any of the Rich or pragmatick Neighbourhood for theſe Places of Truſt and Honour, you cannot eſcape Envy from theſe who think they have leſs Share in the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agment of Affairs, than their vain Pretences gives them in their own weakly grounded, but ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited Imaginations, or in the flattering Apprehenſions of their Friends, Alleys, and expectant Dependents: And there are three ſort of Perſons you may expect will invade your Reputation, and labour to aſperſe your Names, and blacken your Actings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Thoſe who are thruſt from the Government, it is rare to find theſe who by ſome diſaſter are removed from Publick Truſt, or diſappointed of them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend what is praiſe-worthy in their Succeſſors, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent poſſeſſors of theſe Honours:
<note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>Envy heats every one that mounts the Seat from which it ſelf fell, or was put by;</hi> it will aggravate every Misfortune into a Crime, and aſcribe it unto the miſmanagement of thoſe they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to defame with the people: Whatever fall out croſs is charged on them, and as if the moſt Fortuitous Contingencie depended on their Will, or it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to fore know or prevent the extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies the Capricious Humors of the fickle Populace (which like <hi>Reuben</hi>'s glory, is <hi>unſtable as water</hi>) upon ſome unlucky occurrent commit, when either blown on by a <hi>Fuctions Club,</hi> or ſtirrd up by a <hi>Seditious Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> when either egged on by ſome under-hand <hi>Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Whiſperer,</hi> or broke out by chance: No <hi>humane
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93143:21"/>prudence or foreſight can guard against all Inconvenience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> nor the diligence, integrity, or care of the beſt Rulers Prevent the diſorderly effects of ſome unlucky conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, or of jealouſie and ſuſcicion when they enter the giddy Heads, or poſſeſs themſelves in the fickle hearts of the multitude: <hi>The Miſcarriage of a drunken Cabal, the Scuffle of ſome Childiſh and Fooliſh Mechanicks, a ſudden Rupture, a Tumultuous Mutiny, an Accidental Commotion, a Caſual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>proar,</hi> with all the Train of their fatal conſequences, and I know not what, although theſe things break out in the beſt governed Cities in the World as <hi>Madi</hi>'s <hi>tales</hi> (as we ſay) in the Market Alarms in Camps, or the ſlanderous aſperſions of ſome fair and innocent, but unfortunate Females, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and Fomenters of the one, as well as of the other, are ſculking in the Croud, or loſt in the multitude of Informers: Yet theſe and a thouſand ſuch like unlook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for emergents are laid at their door: Nay, as if Nature were at their beck a misfortune by Fire, the diſorderlineſs of the Seaſon, the infectious influence of ſome unhappy Conjunction of the Planets, the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Air, the Sterility of the Earth; Nay (as we ſay) <hi>If a Stone fall from the Clouds,</hi> it is as unjuſtly as maliciouſly imputed to their ill conduct, and that ſometimes by Men, were they at the Stern themſelves, their Sagacity could not foreſee, nor their Prudence ward off, nor their Wit rectify, or their Dexterity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſuch eventual Miſchances, half ſo well to any tolerable uſe for the preſent or future ſecurity of the place. We treat our Governours often as the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Mexicans</hi> do their Kings, whom they accuſe for all the Miſchiefs that befall them, but in this Magiſtrats do but run the fate of that <hi>Divinity</hi> they repreſent, and the <hi>Providence</hi> that inſtall'd them, which is frequently
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93143:22"/>through Ingratitude and Unjuſtice, by Ignorant and Vitious Men, loaded with their own faults, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils they juſtly bring upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>But not only theſe who by a higher Ordinance are removed from theſe places of Government in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whether deſervedly, or upon ſiniſtrous informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome that would <hi>Monopolize</hi> the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Affairs into their own hands, I will not determine; I think I am not much concerned to dive too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly into that, or too plainly declare my opinion therein, but even theſe who are put by their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or diſappointed of their aims in the Regular way of Election, and would wind themſelves into Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will be quarreling your preceedings, and cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically canvaſſing your Actings, how vertuous ſo ever in themſelves, or honeſtly intended, which God knows, that which mainly ſets them a <hi>gaggling</hi> againſt you, is that they are not the Actors nor Contrivers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; I beſeech you behave ſo, as none of theſe may upon ſome Change or Turn of Affairs accuſe you open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of what they now clandeſtinly inveigh againſt you for, the favour of the Court ſhifts it's Quarters, and there may ariſe another <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who will let looſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you other Inquiſitors than you are aware of, who will ſift all your Actings, diſcuſs all your proceedings, and ſtretch on the <hi>Tenters</hi> your muſt pardonable eſcapes, and by this Severity againſt you, ſeek to cover their own Blemiſhes, like thoſe Birds who making a great deal of noiſe, and fluttering with their Wings at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from their Neſts, to divert Paſſengers from find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them nearer hand.</p>
            <p>But though this ſhould not happen, and you were in no fear of being called into an Account by Man; Remember, you have the great King of Heaven and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93143:22"/>Earth to compear before, who will not err through ignorance, or before-ſtall'd through favour, who will not be over-born with Power, or corrupted with Bribes, in paſſing Judgment on you for your Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, nothing will yeeld ſo much Solace and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to you under all the Calumnies of Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Reproaches of evil men, as the joyful Reflection of your Conſciences on your Carriage in your diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Truſts and Stations:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.3.</note> If you can ſay with good <hi>Hezekiah, Remember, O Lord, how I walked before thee in integrity,</hi> in my poſt, whether of <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> or <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> whether of <hi>Judge</hi> or <hi>Barreſter,</hi> this will be a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Wall, an impregnable Fortreſs againſt all the Shocks of envious Competitors, the Clamors of diſcontented Neighbours, &amp; the tumultuous Noiſe of a giddy Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. This will make you <hi>ſtand in Judgment</hi> and look GOD in the Face,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> when the <hi>Wicked</hi> are <hi>driven like Chaff before the Wind</hi> &amp; aſhamed to look up: Believe it, it is more to look GOD in the Face than to look Tygers in the face, Lions in the face, Flams in the face, yea Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; Gibbets, yea Devils and all the Infernal Troup, yet by walking according to the Rules I have preſcribed you, I doubt not but you will do it boldly with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and GOD will Reward you with Joy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But beſide the Difficulties you may meet with from envious, or diſappointed Competitors, you have to do with a <hi>Reſty</hi> untoward eaſily diſcontented Body of Inhabitants:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni populo quid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignum &amp; quaerulum in impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus.</note> the <hi>Common-people is a skittiſh Beast that Kicks at it's Governours,</hi> and <hi>will be ſtill At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to caſt it's Rider,</hi> who are never pleaſed with the beſt Rulers too long, and ſcarce any ſo bad but may pleaſe them for a time, when unjuſtly diſguſted with the preſent Settlement of Affairs: Nor is there any thing more taken with the <hi>MOB,</hi> than what grate the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93143:23"/>ears of their Betters. Aſperſing their Governours, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting from their Superiors, finding or making Faults in their Management of Truſt, Tickles them with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and I have in my own time obſerved them ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver better ſatisfied, than with theſe ſtreperous Haran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues how void ſoever of Reaſon or Senſe, of Piety, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty or Diſcretion, full of Libels and Invectives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Magiſtrats and them in Publick Office: And of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>the greateſt and most zealous Promoters of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-good,
<note place="margin">☞</note> when the Maggot or Caprice takes the many headed Beast, become the Butts of Vulgar Railing, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of Publick Hatred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in this Caſe as good Steers-men in a Storm or Tempeſt mind their Work,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Virtus Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcia fordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae, inta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatis fulgit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus, nec ſumit aut ponit ſecures ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularis aurae.</hi> Horat. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>car.</hi> 2. <hi>Plutarch vit. Fabii.</hi>
               </note> are not hindered by the Noiſe of the Paſſengers or the Clamors of Sea ſick-people, no more ſhould Governours be hindered from, or Retarded in their Adminiſtrations, by the Baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings or Cenſures of an unskilfull and unruly Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; They ſhould with <hi>Fabius</hi> hold on their Courſe, and follow his Example, he was Reviled by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my for deferring giving Battel to <hi>Hannibal,</hi> his Friends told him the Contumely the Souldiers loaded him with upon this ſcore, he anſwered them, <hi>I ſhould be more Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted than they judge me, if for fear of their Reproaches I ſhould abandon my own Reaſon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus homo nobis cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctando re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit Rem, non ponebat ante ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ergo poſtque magiſque viri nunc gloria cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> Vir. <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 854.</note> That Man is not fit to Rule others, nor will he ever Attempt any thing worthy of himſelf or his place, who ſhall be ſtartled or ſhaken from his Poſt with Rumors and Calumnies, for then he degrades &amp; ſubjects himſelf to the <hi>Chimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Fancies of theſe he ought to command.</p>
            <p>Reckon as we ſay then with your ſelves, do never ſo great or good things for the Intereſt of the City, Govern never ſo well, there will ſtill be ſome <hi>Shimeh</hi> or other to Revile you, there will be ſtill ſome to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93143:23"/>from your Merit, Eclipſe your Vertues, and Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your beſt and moſt innocent Actings, but a good Magiſtrat that minds his Buſineſs, is both deaf to the <hi>Barking,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ille velut Rupes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum quae prodit in aequor, obvia ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postaque ponto, ipſa im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mota ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens.</hi> Virgil <hi>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid.</hi> 10. <hi>de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zentio.</hi>
               </note> and as a firm Rock immoveable with the rage of Waves, or fury of Winds: The Serenity of his Mind is as little Diſcompoſed, his Purpoſe for the publick as little altered, by all theſe injurious and invidious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, as we are moved with theſe Showrs, which break their Force on the Stones of the Street, or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our Houſes. Magiſtrats are not compared to <hi>Cooks,</hi> who make Sauces, and prepare Meat for pleaſing Mens liquoriſh Pallats, but to <hi>Phyſicians</hi> who ſearch Sores, pry into Wounds, cleanſe Ulcers, cut Gangre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Limbs, apply Cauſtives and Corroſives, as well as Lenitives, and the Body natural ſtands not in more need of theſe Operations, than the Body Politick of ſuch like in their Kind: A good Magiſtrat who is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to himſelf of doing no baſe or unworthy thing in his publick Capacity, is no more diverted or ſhaken from Managing his Truſt, with the malicious Talk, or ſpitefull Revilings of ſome, than a Phyſician is hindred with the Tears and Cryes of ſome Childiſh Effeminat Patients: He is as little fretted with the Slanders of ſome, who ſet up for Wits and honeſt Men, when they are nothing leſs than ſuch, as he is lifted up with the flattering Complements of fooliſh Friends, or deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Foes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally,</hi> If you would ſtop the Mouths of your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, at leaſt give them no juſt ground to Object againſt you, if you would Anſwer the Ends of your Stations, and advance the <hi>publick Intereſt</hi> of the City, if you would keep up your Eſteem in the Mearts and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93143:24"/>Mouths of it's Inhabitants, let <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Prudence</hi> ſquare your Actings, theſe are the beſt Preſervatives of your Dignity, theſe are the Illuſtrious Vertues which ſtrike Fear and Reverence into the Hearts of thoſe beneath you, and will keep them on their due Hinges within their juſt Bounds. <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſays, <hi>nothing makes one Man Frankly yield Obedience to another, but either Aſſurance of Love, or Opinion of his Integrity or Juſtice who commands;</hi> for we even ſee that Obedience which is due to the higheſt Powers on Earth is a frail thing where theſe are wanting,
<note place="margin">☞</note> and unleſs People have a mixture of Fear and Love, from the Apprehenſion they have of the Worth and Qualities of their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, they are ſoon Debauch'd from their Duty: As the Authority of Men of Power, which is the Attractive of Obedience from their Inferiours, is gained by good Acts, ſo it is loſt by ill, and Majeſty it ſelf void of the neceſſary Vertues and Endowments to ſupport it, dwindles into Contempt, and Diſgrace.</p>
            <p>Let me Addreſs my ſelf to you the People of this <hi>numerous City,</hi> and Exhort you all to Reverence and Obey your Magiſtrats, you ſee how they are expoſed to Dangers, and Toſſ'd with Perplexities, do not imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Charge with reſtleſsneſs and untowardlineſs; it is ungenerous to make their Burden more heavy and uneaſy by your untractableneſs, they Watch that you may Sleep ſoundly, they Toil for your Reſt, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for your Eaſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex quo ſi Regno de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicavit, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi eripuit.</hi> Senec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ad Polybium.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they are in effect and reality the greateſt Servants,</hi> as <hi>Agamemnon</hi> ſays of himſelf in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> It is ſome ſatisfaction to Men in Place, when they abandon the eaſe and ſecurity of a privat State, for <hi>ſerving the Publick,</hi> that they are not at all this pains for an Ingrate or Stubborn People, what Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93143:24"/>will it be to you,
<note place="margin">Plutarch. <hi>vit.</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curg.</note> and Comfort to your Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats if they could Anſwer with the <hi>Spartan Archon,</hi> who Replyed when ſome were attributing the Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and Proſperity of their State, to the Conduct of their Governours, that becauſe their Kings knew beſt to Manage their commanding Power, they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did thrive ſo well, No, ſays he, <hi>but our People of all other know beſt how to Obey,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and hence comes the Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sparta:</hi> So true is that of <hi>Aerſchyſus that ready O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of People is the ſource of their Happineſs;</hi> When Cities are crumbled into Factions, their Strength de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines, their Trade decays, their Wealth is diſſipated, to maintain Parties, their Honour is trampled upon by every <hi>riſing Courtier,</hi> and their Priviledges becomes a Prey to the <hi>Arbitrarineſs</hi> of <hi>Preſumptuous Rulers,</hi> or the <hi>Inſolency</hi> of ſome <hi>Hectoring Grandees,</hi> who take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their Diviſions, and <hi>Fiſh beſt for their own Ends in ſuch troubled Waters:</hi> Obedience to your Magiſtrats, and Unity amongſt your is ſelves the beſt Bull-wark a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Incroachments of Diſdainfull Adverſaries with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, or inteſtine Deſigns of <hi>Pragmatick ſelf-ſeeking</hi> Men within our own Boſom.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Diſcourſe with a word more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly fitted to you the Magiſtrats, and another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to us all in general: For you that are, or in your Turns, may be Governours in this Antient &amp; Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable City, that Tablet which <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antonius</hi> found at <hi>Thebes,</hi> whereon <hi>Ptolomy Arſacides</hi> cauſed write this Proteſtation of his own Behaviour in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his Power, is worth your Regard and Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, the Emperour was ſo much taken with it, he carried it with him to <hi>Rome</hi> as a precious Relique, hung it in his Bed-chamber, left it as a ſingular Treaſure
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93143:25"/>to his Son <hi>Cammodus,</hi> who ſucceeded him in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
            <q>
               <p>I never exalted the Proud Rich Man, neither bated the Poor Juſt Man.</p>
               <p>I never denyed Juſtice to the Poor for his Poverty, nor pardoned the Wealthy for his Riches.</p>
               <p>I never gave Reward through Partial Affection, nor pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed out of Paſſion.</p>
               <p>I never ſuffered evil to eſcape unpuniſhed, nor paſſed by goodneſs unrewarded.</p>
               <p>I never denyed Justice to him that asked it, nor mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to him that deſerved it.</p>
               <p>I never puniſhed in the extremity of mine anger, nor promiſed in the height of my mirth.</p>
               <p>I never did evil out of malice, nor good for By-ends.</p>
               <p>I never opened my gate to the Flatterer, nor my ear to the Backbiter.</p>
               <p>I always ſought to be beloved of the Good, and to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Wicked.</p>
               <p>I always favoured the Poor, who was able to do little, and God who was able to do much, always favoured me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe are as ſo many ſuccinct and nervous <hi>Aphoriſms, pithy Sentences,</hi> worthy to be written in <hi>Golden Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in your <hi>Council-chamber,</hi> but if they be in-print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your hearts, and practiſed in the Exerciſe of your Offices, this is a better Regiſter of ſuch Weighty and excellent Sayings, the effect will make the <hi>City happy, your Souls bleſsed,</hi> and <hi>your Memory honourable</hi> in the City-records, in the mouths of the preſent and ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Generation.</p>
            <p>Let me for the Inſtruction of all, ſubjoyn to this, what that great Light of the <hi>African</hi> Church ſays,
<note place="margin">Auguſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Johan.</note> and may in our ſeveral Stations, be tranſcribed by us all.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:93143:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That Family is moſt firmly establiſhed, where the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the houſe like</hi> Joſhua <hi>is Religious, the Miſtris like</hi> Abigail <hi>Diſcreet and Vertuous, where the Father like</hi> Abraham <hi>is Faithful, the Mother like</hi> Sarah <hi>is Helpful and Induſtrious, the Sons like</hi> Iſaac <hi>Dutiful, Brethren and Siſters like</hi> Laban <hi>and</hi> Rebecca <hi>Cheerful, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants like thoſe of the Centurions Tractable, there is Proſperity and Tranquillity in the Houſe or City, when every one ſtudieth to be quiet, and do his own Buſineſs, when Man and Wife live together in Amity, Brethren and ſiſters in Unity, Companions and Servants in Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, when Superiors give Examples of Integrity, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors diſcharge their Duty, when the elder ſort are Patterns of Sobriety, and the younger ſort Veſsels of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you that are or may be Magiſtrats, obſerve this Proteſtation, and you the Citizens this Inſtruction, you'll be Authors of bleſſing and happineſs to the City, and to one another, the Affairs of the <hi>good Town</hi> will ſucceed proſperouſly. This will make you the Magiſtrats paſs for <hi>gods</hi> in the Scripture-ſenſe, the people will receive your Commands as <hi>Oracles,</hi> this will ſtrike Fear and Reverence towards you, not only when you ſit in your Judicial Seats, with all Enſigns of State and Magnificence, but upon tranſient occaſions, when people meet you, they will be apt to ſay, with thoſe in the Acts of the Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Acts 14.11.</note> 
               <hi>behold the gods are deſcended to us in likeneſs of men,</hi> and our houſes, if we anſwer <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Advice, will be Temples for God, the whole City will become a <hi>Model</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and a <hi>Habitation</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 26.1.</note> God will appoint Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for Walls and Bullwarks.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
